They had a date with fate in Casablanca!
Casablanca is a drama, romance film directed by Michael Curtiz.
In Casablanca, Morocco in December 1941, a cynical American expatriate
meets a former lover, with unforeseen complications.
Rick Blaine, played by Humphrey Bogart.
Ilsa Lund, played by Ingrid Bergman.
Victor Laszlo, played by Paul Henreid.
Captain Louis Renault, played by Claude Rains.
Major Heinrich Strasser, played by Conrad Veidt.
Signor Ferrari, played by Sydney Greenstreet.
Casablanca is a 1942 American romantic drama film directed by Michael Curtiz
and starring Humphrey Bogart, Ingrid Bergman, and Paul Henreid.
Filmed and set during World War II, it focuses on an American expatriate (Bogart) who must choose between his love for a woman (Bergman) and helping her
husband (Henreid), a Czechoslovak resistance leader, escape from the Vichy-controlled city of Casablanca to continue his fight against the Nazis.
The screenplay is based on Everybody Comes to Rick's, an
unproduced stage play by Murray Burnett and Joan Alison.
The supporting cast features Claude Rains, Conrad Veidt, Sydney
Greenstreet, Peter Lorre, and Dooley Wilson.
Warner Bros.
story editor Irene Diamond convinced producer Hal B.
Wallis to purchase the film rights to the play in January 1942.
Brothers Julius and Philip G.
Epstein were initially assigned to write the script.
However, despite studio resistance, they left to work on
Frank Capra's Why We Fight series early in 1942.
Howard Koch was assigned to the screenplay until
the Epsteins returned a month later.
Principal photography began on May 25, 1942, ending on August
3; the film was shot entirely at Warner Bros.
Studios in Burbank, California, with the exception of one
sequence at Van Nuys Airport in Los Angeles.
Although Casablanca was an A-list film with established stars and first-rate writers, no one involved with
its production expected it to stand out among the many pictures produced by Hollywood yearly.
Casablanca was rushed into release to take advantage of the publicity from
the Allied invasion of North Africa a few weeks earlier.
It had its world premiere on November 26, 1942, in New York City and was
released nationally in the United States on January 23, 1943.
The film was a solid, if unspectacular, success in its initial run.
Exceeding expectations, Casablanca went on to win the Academy Award for Best Picture, while Curtiz was
selected as Best Director and the Epsteins and Koch were honored for Best Adapted Screenplay.
Its reputation has gradually grown, to the point that its lead characters, memorable lines, and pervasive theme song
have all become iconic, and it consistently ranks near the top of lists of the greatest films in history.
In the inaugural class of 1989, the United States Library of Congress selected the film as one of the first for
preservation in the National Film Registry for being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film's copyright was renewed in 1970; it will enter the public domain in the US
and countries with the rule of the shorter term on January 1, 2038.
Roger Ebert wrote: "If there is ever a time when they decide that some movies should be spelled
with an upper-case M, Casablanca should be voted first on the list of Movies."
The film explores themes of corruption, nazi, escape, love triangle, resistance.
The tone is dark and emotional.